English subtitle by : Eduun
The late fourth century A.D. the
Roman Empire began to crumble.
Alexandria, in the province of Egypt,
still retained some of its lustre,...
...possessed one of the Seven
Wonders of the ancient world:...
...the legendary lighthouse,
and the biggest library known.
The library was a not only
cultural but a religious symbol,...
a place where the pagans worshiped
their ancestral gods.
The traditional pagan worship
in the city now coexisted...
...with the Jews, and an unstoppable
religion up to now banned,...
...Christianity.
Library of Alexandria, 391 A.D.
After taking the library, many
pagans were converted...
Hipatia continued teaching and
researching,...
...while his former students held...
...important positions in the
social elite.
The empire was split in two forever.
Many Christians saw this as a
sign of the end of the world...
...and decided to prepare by
practicing a more holy life.
The order of "Parabolanos" monks
was charged to go...
...through the streets and watch
for Christian morality...
...now uneven by the presence
of the Jews.
The Library, years later.
How many fools
have wondered
why not the stars fall
from the sky
But you,
not happy to cease of the wise,
You know that the stars
do not move up or down.
only reborn
from east to west,
following the most perfect post
ever can see ,
circle.
Because the circle  reigns
in heaven,
the stars would never have fallen
and never will.
But what about here on Earth?
Here, bodies do fall.
But their movements
are not circular but linear.
Look again.
Again.
No, leave it.
So,
What mysterious wonder
do you would think
that may lurk beneath the earth
for every single person and animal,
and object and all laid exact
on there
What may should be?
The highness, madame.
No.
Sinesio.
The weighty.
No, you both speaking about the same thing,
but you not talking about primary course.
Has anyone ever thought about
your..
your feet ...
your feet
standing perched on the
very center of the cosmos
that holds all things together,
pull them together
If there is no center,
the universe would be
deformed, infinite, formless,
chaotic.
Doesn't matter that we were
here, there or anywhere
What you will do? That's right
never being born
Library of Alexandria 391 AD
God, Our Father,
lord of the universe,
origin of all things,
eternal force of the cosmos,
where everything has
its beginning and its end.
Mighty Serapis,
Isis, Horus,
And all the gods Anubis
that protect us
both in heaven
and on earth ...
Something happens in the market.
I know you also feel something.
I've seen.
Tell the master that we leave.
Can you believe. He was counting me
as the part of their conquests
This Orestes also foolish
as his father.
I have already suggested that you take
his heart to another muse
one more beautiful than me.
- Who?
The music.
Music
He find his music.
What happen 227 had become
16 ?
Divide  with 14.
They behave like humans!
Eat, drink and fornicate!
If my gods  eat, drink
and fornicate, good for them
Know this,
you who console yourself
with pagan images.
Men, women,
birds, reptiles!
Serapis!
Serapis! Who could trust
the God, need a flower pot
for crown?
Hey You, Christians, how arrogant you
to take another
Empire attitude like this
My father's father saw them
slaughtered at the circus
and ate to the lions.
Enough! Watch.
Watch.
You see now
I walk cross the fire.
If my god ...
If my God is the true god,
I unscathed, no hurt.
And if your gods exist,
they'll roast me like a pig.
You ...
You're lie!
You'll burn!
You will have what you deserve!
Let's see if you can walk cross
the fire.
What are you doing?
Stop, you can not do that!
Leave him alone.
Quiet! or you will follow.
Who is this?
How many times should I
must repeat message?
Today,
Christians
burn a man.
Right in the middle of agora!
I will not have this in my house!
Not in the house of Theon!
Give it to me.
Give it to me!
No terrific mercy is way go
- Davo!
Get up.
You have nothing to do
with this.
I do, i am a Christian.
What did you say?
I do. I am a Christian
Punish both of us.
So, now we'll presume to teach
us a mercy
Get a whip.
- Father!
Calm ...
Father, I beg you.
I begged you
wrapped in.. in blazing, right?
To the flames, stupid.
Why did not you burned like the heathen?
Tell me.
Leave us ...
Come here.
Kneel.
Tell me, is true
you are a Christian?
I do not know what to say, madame.
- Why not?
If i say yes, that will be a lie
If I said no, i lied to
my master and I do not know which is worse.
Then say nothing.
That's it.
Thank you.
The master is very angry
himself.
What is that?
Something I've done.
looks like a ...
What is it?
the Ptolemaic system.
Yes it is.
Have you done?
Earth
is the center of the cosmos
and revolve around
the sun
and the five wanderers: Mercury,
Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn.
Never disobeying
the law of the circle.Never
Ptolemy
told me show as do obey.
affected if you see them move
in a loop
is the Join effect of
two circles.
One
travel around the Earth
and the smaller circle
own each wandering.
Loop, the epicycles
"say you see is not happen on the earth"
but our eyes
deceive us.
Well search, Davo.
I like you do the explanation search even
paying course attention or not
One or two..up here
I tell you The Gods should consulted
to me before they creating anything.
Why say that?
It's all so whimsical!
Why is the joint take of
two circles?
Would not be more, perfect
if the wander is..
if wander and a single circle
give sense to everything?
What authority do you judge
the work of God?
What is wrong with you, Christians?
The man is no longer with brief mouth
in this city
Could you decide creation, you could decide
a Lord,
and you offended.
You should move to the desert.
You will not hear anything offensive there.
You know nothing about you speak.
None of you.
What this.. you can explain to all?
What is the question?
Just.. answer me.
If ...
if two things are equal
a third thing,
and They are all equal to each other
Well.
Now, Are you are not similar to me?
Yes
And you, Orestes?
Now I am actually say with everybody
here in this room,
More things you joint us
and divide us.
Whatever happens on the street,
we are brothers.
We are brothers.
Did you remember, the fights are a thing
of slaves and rabble.
Now We should give Davo's presentation
well applause
We will judge all
a live and dead!
And then it will be too late,
because only those who believed in Jesus
we'll be saved.
What are you waiting for?
The Kingdom of God is near.
Do you understand what
I am telling to you?
Yes
Do You understand like man do
or do you not had, like sheep?
What are you looking there?
Yes, you.
What are you looking here?
Are you Ammonius,
who made the miracle?
Do you want to see a miracle?
Are you the one?
I am.
Come with me.
Jesus traveled throughout Galilee
teaching in their synagogues.
Preaching the good news
for you
and curing diseases
people.
In all he talked about Syria
and people came to see him
worldwide.
That's Theophilus.
Bishop.
For theirs is the Kingdom
of Heaven.
Blessed are they that mourn
they shall be comforted.
Blessed are the meek
for they shall inherit the earth.
Blessed are those who have
hunger and thirst for righteousness,
will be satisfied.
The word of God!
Blessed are
the merciful
they will be find mercy.
Blessed are
the pure in heart,
they shall see God.
The Lord be with you.
And you, parabolans.
So how did you escape the flames?
"The Lord be with you.
"And with you.
What did you think?
I am pray!
Should probably you not even know how.
What you got in your sack?
- Do you have Food?
It is for my master.
What's wrong with you?
I have to pay that
with my own money!
What do you need the money for?
Look at the faces.
Here.
I want you to try it yourself
and after it work i will
teach you how to pray.
Look forward.
"The Lord be with you.
"Bless you.
See?
That is the miracle!
go on, keep doing.
The Lord be with you.
Please.
Thank you.
Bless you,
Parabolans
Bless you.
Hi slave
What is your name?
Davo.
Davo the slave!
You look like a true parabolans.
A true soldier of Christ.
What do they say now?
telling them to dance.
The men now happy
with wine.
All aboard!
How unlucky!
Save your servants!
End the last two!
Thank you, the audience.
Excuse to delay
what we watching around
to change...off.
Good evening
Forgive my boldness.
I am Orestes,
son of Orestes.
I am here. ..
I here to declare my love
for Hypatia, the philosopher,
whole no doubt know.
some time, i following the ..,
I have dedicated myself to music
hope so seeking solace
in the harmony of it sound.
But for me,
such harmony
only found in my lady.
so,
I prepare here just want
offer my melody
and i hope to ...
Stop talking.
That man will go far.
If I prefer bananas
not figs, I would have ready falls
at his feet.
What did to prepares to present
Me?
How?
Gratty, can you order your daughter's hat.
Would you to prepare to marry her?
My Hypatia subject to a man?
Without read and to teach?
For even speak her mind?
the most brilliant philosopher
i know, hanging to give up the science
No, could be death to her.
It's true.
Her work is admirable.
Yes wise and virtuous.
But Theon,
do not forget their plight.
She's a Woman, Right?.
Our Father
who art in heaven ...
Do not let it be another.
Please do not let
it is another.
Do not let anyone.
Do not let it be another.
Amen.
Good day, ma'am.
Good day.
Good day lady.
Yesterday many people see
on your colleague  present....
I accepted the gift.
And today I want to give
something back.
This is for you.
It is the blood of my cycle.
Orestes  ...
You say you have found
harmony in me.
Then I suggesting you look out elsewhere
because i think is very little harmony on you
or beauty in that.
Do not you agree?
Yesterday we were discussing
the Apollonius cone.
We speak of the circle,
of the ellipse and parabola.
Today we see the hyperbola.
- Lady!
Forgive me, Lady.
Olimpios requires your present
urgently to Serapeum.
To you as well.
Thank you, Lord.
How is to enjoy that make us
swallow the faith
and customs the people until
recently were coming out rule?
- What happened?
- It's a sacrilege!
Christians
have met in the agora.
They mocking the gods.
Must stop
these insults!
He may not fear him,
But fear our swords!
Wait!
What is it you are going to do?
Are you going to attack them?
Are you going to staying your hands
with blood for an insult?
The gods!
An insult to
the gods!
If you feel so bad,
Report them to the prefect.
It might seem that you protecting them.
i try to protect
our disciples.
You, who are inciting them to be murderers.
Theon, as director,
you have the last word.
The insult must to be answered.
The Jews can do what they
want, is not your battle.
Ask to your Christians, you would do well
join us with your rank.
You will not caused my disciples
out of this house!
- Glory to Serapis!
- Now all the gods!
Wait for my command!
No one should suspect
until we have surrounded.
for slaves!
Slaves present yourselves
Slaves also someone!
Davo, back.
No. Back.
To the Christians!
Glory to Serapis!
Let us listen now!
Do you hear her complain?
No!
This one have no voice too!
Their mouths do not speak,
their eyes do not see,
his nose does not smell.
Still pagans
until they kneel before them!
What madness is this?
By the gods!
Medoro!
Take care of your master!
Protect it..!
God is one!
Death for the heathens!
You! What are you looking that?
Keep fight!
A fight!
Are you deaf?
I said that to fight
I am a Christian!
- What is Christ?
- Christ is one!
Death to the heathens!
God is one!
No! No!
the entrance,
We must defend the entrance!
What's happening?
Our men retreat,
Your father attack by Christians!
Father!
No problem. No problem.
What happened?
It was his slave.
Davo, bring rags and water, quickly.
Father  ...
Synesius, we must leave here.
Hold it.
Parabolans are coming!
God is with us!
Hallelujah! Hallelujah!
- Close the door!
- Our men still out there!
May the gods protect them.
Close the gate..!
Do not kill him! It will be a hostage,
like the others. Did you hear everyone?
Any Christian that you catch
to be a hostage.
Take the our injured to the temple
and Christians
to the basement. Anyone had good eye, good aim
up on the walls.
Olimpio.
This one is Christian.
Yes, and these three as well.
If you are Christian,
go to the basement.
Olimpios...
is my brothers, I will go as
prisoner with them.
If necessary, so do that.
If anyone,
anyone,
dares laying finger on
one of my brothers,
I swear I will cross.
Look!
Look at this!
Orestes.
Thank you.
When is
so many Christians?
We will have to negotiate.
Tell me what can we expect
of a Christian emperor
except we put the soul
accept positive still being alive
that's it.
This is fine.
Nobody leaves
the group, please.
Are they going to pray all night?
Davo.
Stay here.
It's save here.
Just stay with him.
Synesius! What are you doing?
Lady, sister and mother,
God bless and protect you.
Back!
end up ....
slave not eating this
Slaves in the bottom!
three comes out
It's a disaster.
Father, why you laid the dice.
Do you seem healed today?
-No.
- No?
Let's see.
Promise me, my child,
when i'm done.You want remember
this foolish old man.
I promise.
Remember me as i was before.
before when i could still think.
I. ..
work with you.
And I listened to you.
How could I've been so wrong?
See. you here, locked
because my fault y. ..
Father, please.
I wanted you to be free.
I am free.
Hi Christians
Christians!
What's that call 'bout the god damn
you doing now?
Coffins for you, scum!
tell me.
Where are the gods now?
Where are they?
You'd better find another
- Other?
Which one? The God of the Christians?
such a fool!
What do you think, Lady?
You are so bold
Turn off the fire.
Yes, you bold.
Very bold.
I've been thinking about something
you talk to me.
Me?
The day that you criticize
celestial mechanism
and i call it
- when it's call.
Yes,.thought..
actually
i criticizing Ptolemy
complicate everything
with epicycles.
But I do not know.
i have simple minded.
No.
the heavens
should be simple.
So am I right or..?
what if ...
What if there were simple
explanation about the wanders
There is.
But it's so absurd, so old
that no one is give it credit.
What theory is that?
Theory Aristarchus
Aristarchus argued
that the earth moves.
The behavior of the wandering
is only an optical illusion
produced by our movement
in combination with his
around the sun.
-A heliocentric model.
That's right.
The sun would be at the center,
as it his deal
King of the stars.
And make as just.. be another wanderer.
His work was lost
in the fire that destroyed
mother's library.
That's way we have to take great
care of this place.
Our library
is all that remains
the wisdom of men.
But every time dropping an object ...
Who speaks?
Forgive me mistress, love.
i was listening.
Speak up, Davo.
If the earth is moving,
every time dropping an object,
should fall further behind.
And the wind always blow
against us.
And the birds would be wipe on.
I told you
the hypothesis of Aristarchus
that no sense at all.
I feel that what you said
be refuted.
But right now I do not know how.
Make way for the prefect!
Make way!
Listen everyone!
Prepare to listen and obey
the verdict of our emperor
I, Flavius
Theodosius Augustus
emperor and supreme Head
of the provinces of the Orion,
having been informed
the event notice
recently in city Alexandria,
hereby declare and command
let me insurgents
be forgiven and released ...
In exchange for my generosity,
the insurgents leave the Serapeum
and the Library immediately
allowing
Christians to enter
and make use of facilities
whatever you like.
What can we expect?
We destroy everything!
Pagans will
leave ..!
The Books.
And they will be escorted
to their homes.
Obey immediately!
Keep yourself together!
Send half a regiment
the other side.
We will send the rest later.
Yes, sir.
Prefect.
I want they may not contain
long.
On the cross! On the cross!
Keep yourself together!
Let the minor works!
- What are the minor works?
- take only important!
The soldiers retreated!
Slave
- Have you seen my mistress?
- Just get out here and help!
- We can not with so many!
We need for help.
Please don't get my father here.
Slave
Come on!
Come on, quickly!
Hypatia and her students
follow in the atrium.
Are they crazy?
If they want, let them burn.
Come on!
Quickly!
Lady.
Where were you?
Take out that sack.
Lady We have to go.
- Take out the sack
My slaves never around
when you need it.
I was ...
- Move move quickly!
Idiot!
Run!
This no time!
Lady!
We gotta go.
You have to leave.
God is one!
Run!
Davo!
Where are you going?
- We gotta go!
- Where are you going?
If you want to die
by our gods, let him.
Davo, do not.
- Come on!
- Davo!
- Davo, no!
- Come!
By the cross
Alleluia, alleluia, alleluia!
Slave
Davo!
Davo the slave!
Help me with this!
Help!
Alleluia, alleluia, alleluia!
Pagan scum!
The most of wound be ulcerated.
I know.
Davo.
Davo!
You are free.
Go.
From now on, in Alexandria
only permitted ceremonies
Christian and Jewish.
pagan sacrifices,
the worship of pagan symbols
and visits to pagan temples
are prohibited.
If someone makes such acts
or even look at the statues
of their ancient gods,
shall be punished without mercy.
Damn Jews!
They're just a bunch of thugs,
a bunch of animals.
Joran, my dear friend, calm down.
Let Bishop Cyril
begun his own depend.
Prefect
our blessed parabolans,
Hung hi has just called
me..? the bird,
default them self ..
strong enough to carry loads
repel, six,
levers ...
And stones!
Prefect can carry stones.
I know they was enter the theater
and stoned knowing we'll do nothing
to defend
Non sense. Because it is the Sabbath!
On the Sabbath you should
honor God
in your synagogues
instead stopping yourself
set in theater.
Therefore I showered stones.
Prefect, you hear that?
Now he threatened us. It is too much..
Friends, there are more things that unite
us than divide us.
We are brothers!
We are all brothers
Where would you Christians be
without the Jews?
Jesus was a Jew!
Jesus was Jewish!
There is .a .something I find
stubbing what You've told.
- What?
Well,
Why Cyril begin
to cleaning up the city?
is he not satisfied
with what they already have?
He just wants to scare the Jews.
but why you say then before..
What if really interesting.. you
and not them?
Me?
Why?
I'm as Christian as he.
Yes, but forget
that many of your friends
that circle are not.
A full sail, prefect.
Lets go.
-Aspasius, you ready?
Yes, mistress.
I would like you to take the sack
and flying to top the mast.
And now, Lady,
Will you finally tell me what
the point?
When Aspasius
drop the sack, the boat
will be moving forward.
Therefore, the sack
not fall at the foot of the mast,
but will fall further back.
About ...
here.
And what's so special about that?
- Yes!
- But You're wrong!
Yes, but this is definitely
proved
definitive. The sack
has behaved as if
the boat stationary.
What does that mean?
i do not know.
But the same principle can
be applied to the Earth.
we could be moving around the sun
without our knowledge.
-Aristarchus.
Exactly.
Why are you troubled yourself
by that, Lady?
Ptolemy  not perfect,
but it works.
Orestes, as this with you warrior ...
A few years ago you was not
so pragmatic, prefect.
A few years ago i spoke first
before thinking.
I have Cepheus  third.
37.
48.
Venus and Mars
share house in Aquarius.
My father would have celebrated
something like a good wine.
The stars will not fall.
- Really?
No, because they are subject
to the hood.
The lid opens two heart
and Jesus will appear.
What chance for you talking about?
Do not you know that the universe
is a huge chest, don't you?
They laid on top
and the Earth ground.
In this idiot not been told
that the Earth is round!
The Earth is flat.
Your head is really flat.
Read the Scriptures!
If the earth is round,
Why not the people that live
in the bottom, fall out?
What about the one sides?
Why not slip?
Think about it.
Davo knows.
hi Brother.
What do you say?
Does the earth is flat or round?
Only God knows these things.
Leave them in the ground!
Where they are belong!
Lady, do not despair.
Today in the boat you make
great progress.
Why do the wandering very
that rightness
so unexpected?
And what is worse,
Why does the sun?
Why is change size
summer to winter?
Perhaps it's because
sometimes is nearer
and sometimes farther?
But Aspasia
watch.
According Aristarchus, the sun must be
in the center of everything.
With us, the Earth,
traveling in a circle around him.
Therefore,
and this is the key
We are always exactly
same ...
distance.
If, as you say,
accept that changes the distance,
that forces us to add
epicycle into orbit
Earth.
To be closer
and then farther away.
Now then we fall
in the same trap as Ptolemy.
-circles upon circles.
- Exactly!
I do not know how to solve
this conflict.
let me know we can do it
if shifting the center  ..well.
And not having a center
My heart, Aspasia.
So,
What do we do?
Resting, lady.
Parabolans!
- Parabolans!
- What happens?
parabolans, quick!
Help!
San Alejandro is on fire!
It is a fire.
Come on!
Gather water! The cube!
Take it!
Hurry!
Come, come!
Parabolans!
Parabolans, quick!
Where's the fire?
Jews! It's a trap.
It's a trap!
Christians all
last night is one night was deplorable.
Now I say to you .
Grave no longer
for our dead brothers.
weep not.
Said you killed for the others,
but they are executioners.
Yes, yes.
Weep for them.
Then they
they know neither God,
neither love nor holiness.
I do not know.
because in this day
who repeated the Scriptures
without understanding at all.
It is they who saw
only a man
when the Son of God
standing on the front of us.
And it is they who
in their blindness mocked Him
and crucified him.
Yes
Weep!
Weep for the Jews,
the murderers of our Lord.
Because God ...
God has already condemned.
It is God will..
to live as slaves,
cursed and exiled
until the end of time.
Damn and exiles!
Lady, do not stop, Lady.
Now whole the Jews
want revenge!
I'm afraid you do not understand
what is really happening.
When this is over,
would be no more Jews in Alexandria.
Sorry to interrupt like this.
Lady, you know risk
to coming here.
Where are the troops?
Why do not more soldiers
on the streets?
No army can contain
entire city.
Calling to the annihilation
of Women and Children
A bishop!
- A Christian!
Then lock him up.
Prefect
You should have an arrested.
not so easy.
Lady,
Cyril knows we both share
the same faith.
That place our prefect
in the
very out of position.
If he defends the Jews,
half the city will rise
against this government.
I see.
But if you do nothing now,
I believe that Cyril
will continue do the same thing
over and over again
until no people
for this government to govern.
How naive with me.
How naive I was to think
with Jews.
Jews out!
is the first kill them
and then buried them.
The Bishop of Cyrene.
- What is he doing here?
I'll find out
It's my little library
of Alexandria.
This is where I teach children.
A cone of Apollonius.
Yes, I did it to teach
the four corners.
Circle,
the ellipse ...
Orestes and should be here
by now.
The parabole
and hyperbola.
It's beautiful.
Often I look and wonder
why the circle co axis
is such impure shapes.
What i get to sit here
again
I bored you.
A long time not do nothing
to hit my head.
And there are more important issues
to deal with.
Forgive me.
Two Christians in the hands
of a pagan.
It's outrageous!
outrageous.
- How many?
I do not know, but it will stink.
Ammonium.
Does God speak to you?
All the time.
Ammonium> this, Ammonius that.
Ammonia, Ammonia, Ammonium ...''
Today he spooked to me
so quickly that I had to asking
slow down
Tell me something.
Did you ever think
what is taken?
Why?
who's forgiven,
but now,
I can not forgive.
Forgive?
Who?
Jews?
Jesus forgave on the cross.
Jesus was God
and only he can show
such leniency.
How dare you
to compare yourself to God?
Brother.
You're still alive.
Why?
Because it was
His will save us
on the stones.
God wants us here,
doing what we do.
To believe in that belief?
My Lord ...
Cyril is very proud man.
Agree to meet but will not discuss
the Jews, only discuss peace.
Peace?
My suggestion, as your humble adviser
in this case,
you accept.
Let peace be the first.
Lady, what do you think?
No..I ...
It does not seem very encouraging.
Why would I want to come
to see Orestes
-without concrete proposals?
something else
He want come to you.
Demands that you see in the Library
during the service on Sunday.
In the Library?
Why?
Only Christians have entered
there since its looting.
It is a provocation!
I'll make a suggestion.
If you think that your presence
so essential
Why not let you baptize?
Most of us,
beginning
by the prefect,
have accepted Christ.
Why not the rest of you?
only a matter of time and you know it!
Really?
Is it only a matter of time?
Excuse me,
Honorable Member
but far time away..
your God has not yet proved
more judge or more compassionate
than their predecessors.
Lady.
Is it really just a matter of time
before I accept your faith?
Why, then,
should this assembly
accept the consult of
someone who ability dilution
absolutely nothing?
I believe in philosophy.
Philosophy.
Just what we need
in such times.
Enough!
I've been studying
absolutely no life.
for my own
And I wonder
wow.
- Forget about what i said today.
Is all
life holds for me?
What else?
I doubt anyone can see
as devoted wife
and mother.
I think ...
I think the whole city
know the history of the handkerchief.
So ...
My father loved that one.
Even  he ...
Who have the loved?
Except you,
Lebanon.
If only I could ...
fathom this ...
a little more.
And get a little closer
the response,
then ...
enough go to grave, happy.
Why?
Why that's mean so much to you?
Right now,
this every second,
whole earth could be moving
and no one realized it.
Except you and me
Believe me Lady, it's best
that nobody notices.
Really not it important?
i Do not understand why you insist
moving the ground they walk on.
Dress yourself
what happened on the boat.
Yes i dit,But that does not mean
this sailing on the earth moves.
What if it does
Hypatia, look around.
Death,
horror
destruction.
If the stars move in
the Circle,
why they share
perfection with us
So we are not moving.
In circle.
We do not move ...
circle.
We move in circles.
Since Plato,
all of them: Aristarchus
Hipparchus, Ptolemy,
all have tried
reconcile their observations
with circular orbits.
but What happen
otherwise hidden
Another way?
Lady, There is no purer than the
circle, you yourself have taught us.
I know, but suppose
that the purity
the circle
prevented us from seeing beyond.
Just like the sunshine
prevents us from seeing
stars.
I must begin again
with new eyes.
I have to rethink everything.
All.
Reading the first letter
Paul to Timothy.
I therefore wish
that everywhere
men would lift their prayers
without anger or disputes.
Equally,
that women desire
dress modestly,
decency and propriety
without braids in her hair
or gold or pearls
or expensive clothes,
-but with good deeds.''
- Why read this passage?
I do not know, I promise
which is not agreed.
Let the woman learn
quiet and full submission,
i can't allow a woman
to teach or have authority
over a man,
but to be
silent
This is the word of God!
Amen.
Jesus himself
knew this when
he entrusted his sacred legacy
twelve men.
Men.
Nothing woman among them.
And yet,
know some in Alexandria
they admire and even trust
in words
obey woman.
The philosopher Hypatia.
A woman who declare,
in public, her impiety.
A witch!
Dignitaries,
is the time for you all
reconciled yourself to Christ.
This is the word of God.
Kneel before her
and accept its truth.
Kneel.
She not you going to kneel?
Kneel!
Sinner
I am a Christian
- I am a Christian!
- No you are!
I'm as Christian as you
Make way for the prefect!
Make way!
I am a baptized Christian!
I'll kill you.
i'm as Christian as you
i'm as Christian as you are
It's to be  possible?
the guilty being executed .
Take me to the Prefect immediately.
- He himself has ordered
you stay at home
until further notice.
At the moment your presence on the street
now not advisable
For what reason?
Cyril make
serious allegations against you.
and them. ..
What is he accused me out?
on Godlines.....
And witchcraft.
I see.
Are you something
worried about, Lady?
No.
Tell me what concerns you.
Prefect, that bites.
Speak.
The Bishop of Cyrene want to see you.
Everybody go.
The wound is still not ...
out. Out!
Everyone out!
without went well.
Do you think I had about this?
But Had she face here
if to betray you?
- are you blind?
Yes, i was blind.
It was my head
what he's wanted for all along
is me.
That snake loves me.
This government!
This city!
Listen .
There will be war.
I know.
Then swear your allegiance to me.
To the Empire. Do it.
Condemn him or get out.
I will do it
On my knees, if necessary.
nut Not only that.
in day i can gather with other bishops
any monks who desert against Cyril.
But I must ask you question.
Orestes, Do you believe in Jesus?
What?
-  do you believe in Jesus?
- I was!
Are you a true Christian
or did you like so many others,
only competent
-booster in politics?
-Sinesio.
Why do not you kneel?
- What choice did i have?
- Why?
What choice did i have?
To betray Hypatia?
condemn her?
would do?
I never offend God.
It is he who offends God.
He depending in.. he..Christian..
Christian..is words to Use the Scriptures ...
just read
what is written.
How many women do you obey
How many?
How many give you admire and ...
Only
one.
Only one.
The Scriptures ...
The Scriptures is corrected
and were in their hands.
Brother, do not you see?
Do not see the insult to God
front of everyone?
I do not know ...
I do not know what ....
you tell him .
don't tell me orestes , you believe me
what is written.
Don't tell me, do you? ...
Tell Him
Tell God.
Kneel!
many other was remember today the miracles
of our love brother in life.
Like the time he commanded himself to
Father and threw himself
in to the fire and wasn't
scorched.
Ammonia,
Death defending your faith
in Christ,
I proclaimed you one mother,
a saint.
From now on
you shall be known as
Saint Taumasius.
we want justice!
Justice!
May God show us the way, my dear
parabolani.
Little more can I say to you.
What about monks of Nitria?
has at least 500 of them.
plus 500 ...
of our men?
I think is enough, It's prefect!
You have whole army to protect.
Listen!
Why did can not we do more
easy and effective?
What do you talking about?
We can hurts........
How?
That a whore.
- Who?
What if we dared
to look at the world just as it is
let's shake for a moment
every preconceived ideas.
What shape would it show us?
what shape
You said once the problem
is the inconsistency of the sun.
Yes I did, good..good
Put it into words.
The sun must be at the center
as we turned around.
And at the same time
in another position seen the
distance from it varies.
Yes, exactly.
- How?
How could occupy
two position?
How can occupy
two position at once?
two position ?
Aspasius ...
Yes, yes. There.
And the other one here.
Maintaining the same proportion.
Okay.
Tie this end there.
Aspasia
imagines that this is Earth
and the each of flames represent the two
extreme positions of the sun relation to it:
in winter and summer.
What happen if both positions
were the two centers
of the same circle
That is impossible, mistress.
wait what we know about the circle?
We know that center of the circles
is always same distance to any point
its perimeter.
Exactly.
Yes.
What if the center divided into two
but keep constant the sum
distances to its perimeter
Okay, I'll show you what.
As I move this rod along
the rope,
a segment increases
and the other decreases.
And vice versa.
Thus the sum of the two always..
constant. You see that?
We apply this, to the movement
Earth?
What ...
will be ...
obtained ?
An ellipse!
An ellipse with the sun
in one focus.
Because,
what is the circle but
special ellipse
whose foci are so close
to get that seem one
complete and ready, Aspasia.
i mean That is, what is this?
Maybe i just .. ..
Perhaps you ...
What do you think?
This could be solved, mistress.
Well done, we will
with this tomorrow.
Get some sleep.
Good night, mistress.
Good night.
Thank you.
Davo!
What are you doing?
Lady.
Let me see.
Why do not you sit down?
Where is everybody?
Please sit down.
I have..
I have news too.
All the dignitaries
that have not yet embraced
Christian faith
should be baptized
in public.
The aim very clear:
add to our cause
all Christians in the city,
decent people, better
to fight for me.
You speak of battling faith.
Okay.
It's seem already decided, I do not understand
to that required my presence here.
I'm not a member of the government.
no you're more than that.
You are the person that i trust most,
and everyone knows it.
It might say that.
Lady.
years ago ...
Years ago you taught us something.
If ...
If two are
equal to one another,
all are equal to each other.
Do you remember?
Yes
All three of us, we are good people!
And you are so Christian
as we are!
Synesius, no doubt question
that you believe.
You can not do.
I must do.
Well ...
For it is a pity,
lady.
A great pity.
Our revered teacher
get away from what
yourself taught
Or do you think I know the madness
that plots
- Synesius!
The Earth revolves around the sun.
What next?
you must let me go.
Let me in!
- I talk to her!
- A parabolans?
- Lady!
Go away before they arrested you.
- Go!
- Aspasius!
I, Davo. I Davo!
Let me go.
- Tell them who I am!
- Do you know this man?
Yes What do you want?
I need to talk to her.
Where is she?
Mistress is not here.
- It is so urgent! Where is she?
she is in the prefect palace.
- Where?
- The prefect palace!
The palace. Thank you.
-Get out of here.
Who was that?
It was a slave once .
Wait, please!
i beg you
If you not agree,
I can no longer protect you.
..a word bible too, have feeling
with you.
......
Hypatia.
Do not you see?
I can not go without you.
I can not.
Without you I can't beat Cyril.
Orestes.
Cyril has already won.
Thank you.
I do not need you.
Davo!
Brother! Where are you going?
We found her!
Whore, walk!
Move, sinner!
- whore!
- Pagan scum!
Witch!
Pagan scum!
Walk! Come on!
Witch!
Strip her!
Get up.
That's it .So the God can be hold
in all your filthy, whore.
the way you knock ...
- ..The prefect so hard?
- Pagan!
whore.
look,
she's not reacting.
she's scream all right
with the skin on the knife.
- How many of you have a knife?
- None
Do not stand your hands
with impure blood.
Lets cool her!
This witch get some stones.
- Quickly!
Whatever we threw Orestes
he still here.
I'll stay with her.
She has fainted.
The body of Hipatia was mutilated
and the remains...
...were dragged through the streets
and burned in a fire.
Orestes was outlawed forever
and Cirilo...
...took control of the power
in Alexandria.
Later, Cirilo was declared a Saint
and Doctor of the Church.
Although not any of Hipatia works
remains,
it is known that she was an
exceptional astronomer,
well-known for the mathematical
study of conical curves.
One thousand, two hundred years later,
in the 17th century, astronomer
Johannes Kepler...
...described that one of those curves,...
...the ellipse, governs the movement
of the planets.