English subtitle by : Eduun
The late fourth century A.D. the
Roman Empire began to crumble.
Alexandria, in the province of Egypt,
still retained some of its lustre,...
...possessed one of the Seven
Wonders of the ancient world:...
...the legendary lighthouse,
and the biggest library known.
The library was a not only
cultural but a religious symbol,...
a place where the pagans worshiped
their ancestral gods.
The traditional pagan worship
in the city now coexisted...
...with the Jews, and an unstoppable
religion up to now banned,...
...Christianity.
Library of Alexandria, 391 A.D.
After taking the library, many
pagans were converted...
Hipatia continued teaching and
researching,...
...while his former students held...
...important positions in the
social elite.
The empire was split in two forever.
Many Christians saw this as a
sign of the end of the world...
...and decided to prepare by
practicing a more holy life.
The order of "Parabolanos" monks
was charged to go...
...through the streets and watch
for Christian morality...
...now uneven by the presence
of the Jews.
The Library, years later.
How many fools
have wondered
why not the stars fall
from the sky
But you,
not happy to cease of the wise,
You know that the stars
do not move up or down.
only reborn
from east to west,
following the most perfect post
ever can see ,
circle.
Because the circle  reigns
in heaven,
the stars would never have fallen
and never will.
But what about here on Earth?
Here, bodies do fall.
But their movements
are not circular but linear.
Look again.
Again.
No, leave it.
So,
What mysterious wonder
do you would think
that may lurk beneath the earth
for every single person and animal,
and object and all laid exact
on there
What may should be?
The highness, madame.
No.
Sinesio.
The weighty.
No, you both speaking about the same thing,
but you not talking about primary course.
Has anyone ever thought about
your..
your feet ...
your feet
standing perched on the
very center of the cosmos
that holds all things together,
pull them together
If there is no center,
the universe would be
deformed, infinite, formless,
chaotic.
Doesn't matter that we were
here, there or anywhere
What you will do? That's right
never being born
Library of Alexandria 391 AD
God, Our Father,
lord of the universe,
origin of all things,
eternal force of the cosmos,
where everything has
its beginning and its end.
Mighty Serapis,
Isis, Horus,
And all the gods Anubis
that protect us
both in heaven
and on earth ...
Something happens in the market.
I know you also feel something.
I've seen.
Tell the master that we leave.
Can you believe. He was counting me
as the part of their conquests
This Orestes also foolish
as his father.
I have already suggested that you take
his heart to another muse
one more beautiful than me.
- Who?
The music.
Music
He find his music.
What happen 227 had become
16 ?
Divide  with 14.
They behave like humans!
Eat, drink and fornicate!
If my gods  eat, drink
and fornicate, good for them
Know this,
you who console yourself
with pagan images.
Men, women,
birds, reptiles!
Serapis!
Serapis! Who could trust
the God, need a flower pot
for crown?
Hey You, Christians, how arrogant you
to take another
Empire attitude like this
My father's father saw them
slaughtered at the circus
and ate to the lions.
Enough! Watch.
Watch.
You see now
I walk cross the fire.
If my god ...
If my God is the true god,
I unscathed, no hurt.
And if your gods exist,
they'll roast me like a pig.
You ...
You're lie!
You'll burn!
You will have what you deserve!
Let's see if you can walk cross
the fire.
What are you doing?
Stop, you can not do that!
Leave him alone.
Quiet! or you will follow.
Who is this?
How many times should I
must repeat message?
Today,
Christians
burn a man.
Right in the middle of agora!
I will not have this in my house!
Not in the house of Theon!
Give it to me.
Give it to me!
No terrific mercy is way go
- Davo!
Get up.
You have nothing to do
with this.
I do, i am a Christian.
What did you say?
I do. I am a Christian
Punish both of us.
So, now we'll presume to teach
us a mercy
Get a whip.
- Father!
Calm ...
Father, I beg you.
I begged you
wrapped in.. in blazing, right?
To the flames, stupid.
Why did not you burned like the heathen?
Tell me.
Leave us ...
Come here.
Kneel.
Tell me, is true
you are a Christian?
I do not know what to say, madame.
- Why not?
If i say yes, that will be a lie
If I said no, i lied to
my master and I do not know which is worse.
Then say nothing.
That's it.
Thank you.
The master is very angry
himself.
What is that?
Something I've done.
looks like a ...
What is it?
the Ptolemaic system.
Yes it is.
Have you done?
Earth
is the center of the cosmos
and revolve around
the sun
and the five wanderers: Mercury,
Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn.
Never disobeying
the law of the circle.Never
Ptolemy
told me show as do obey.
affected if you see them move
in a loop
is the Join effect of
two circles.
One
travel around the Earth
and the smaller circle
own each wandering.
Loop, the epicycles
"say you see is not happen on the earth"
but our eyes
deceive us.
Well search, Davo.
I like you do the explanation search even
paying course attention or not
One or two..up here
I tell you The Gods should consulted
to me before they creating anything.
Why say that?
It's all so whimsical!
Why is the joint take of
two circles?
Would not be more, perfect
if the wander is..
if wander and a single circle
give sense to everything?
What authority do you judge
the work of God?
What is wrong with you, Christians?
The man is no longer with brief mouth
in this city
Could you decide creation, you could decide
a Lord,
and you offended.
You should move to the desert.
You will not hear anything offensive there.
You know nothing about you speak.
None of you.
What this.. you can explain to all?
What is the question?
Just.. answer me.
If ...
if two things are equal
a third thing,
and They are all equal to each other
Well.
Now, Are you are not similar to me?
Yes
And you, Orestes?
Now I am actually say with everybody
here in this room,
More things you joint us
and divide us.
Whatever happens on the street,
we are brothers.
We are brothers.
Did you remember, the fights are a thing
of slaves and rabble.
Now We should give Davo's presentation
well applause
We will judge all
a live and dead!
And then it will be too late,
because only those who believed in Jesus